<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R5/fhir-single.xsd">
	<p>
    This domain contains two mapping tables.  The first is similar to the other domains and covers the SDTM and CDASH specification.  The second covers the CDISC LAB specification.  It is handled as a separate table because it has a significantly larger number of data elements than the other two specifications and the element names have less correlation.  Readability of the mappings was enhanced by moving the content to a separate specification.
  </p>
  <p>
    Lab data in FHIR is handled by two primary resources:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}diagnosticreport.html">DiagnosticReport</a> which covers the overall report of a collection of lab reports</li>
    <li><a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}observation.html">Observation</a> which handles the individual data measurements within an overall lab report</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    The CDISC specifications focus almost exclusively on the latter.  As a result, mappings in both tables are expressed from the perspective of an Observation-rooted transformation.  (I.e. All paths are rooted in Observation or are driven by a search based on Observation.)  For studies interested in the retrieval of legacy lab information, it may in some cases be necessary to retrieve the DiagnosticReport and manually extract information from a PDF or other report representation.  Obviously no standardized mapping can be provided here to assist with that.
  </p>
  <p>
    In FHIR, the Observation resource is used for a wide range of data collection purposes.  In addition to lab data, it is also used to capture vital signs, patient symptoms, psychological assessments, device data, and others.  Ideally, lab data can be distinguished from types of Observations using the Observation.category element which should, ideally, have a code of <code>laboratory</code> drawn from the <a href="http://terminology.hl7.org/1.0.0/CodeSystem-observation-category.html">http://terminology.hl7.org/CodeSystem/observation-category</a>.  However, the core FHIR specification does not mandate the use of this code or system.  (The U.S. Realm implementation guide and several other national implementation guides <b>do</b> mandate the use of this category.)
  </p>
  <p>
    The 'laboratory' category encompasses both simple chemical measurements as well as complex assessments including the description of genetic variants, microbiology tests, etc.  This implementation guide focuses only on simple measurements and does not attempt to map more complex structures - which in some cases correspond to distinct CDISC domains.  In part, this is because FHIR has not yet tried to enforce standardized representation of more complex areas, though intial work has been completed on the capture of genetic findings.  Future versions of this implementation guide will likely tackle more complex lab structures.
  </p>
  
  <a name="mappings"> </a>
  <h3>LB Mappings</h3>
  {% include LB-table.xml %}

  <a name="lab-mappings"> </a>
  <h3>LAB Mappings</h3>
  {% include LAB-table.xml %}

</div>
